# Dr. Ricardo L. Colasanti

CONTACT

Home:

Information 1469 West Carmen Ave

Skype: riccolasanti

Apt 1-south

Skype: riccolasanti

Chicago

E-mail: ric.colasanti@gmail.com

Voice: (001) 773 944-0536

Illinois 60640 USA WWW:https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/195824611/CV

Work (a): Work (b):

University of Chicago Argonne National Laboratory

Searle Chemistry Laboratory Building 240

5735 South Ellis Avenue 9700 South Cass Avenue

Chicago Argonne

Illinois 60637 USA Illinois 60439 USA

Profile

I am a proficient and committed scientific researcher with expertise in scientific computing and a strong background in computational evolutionary and adaptive systems (ALife), in particular cellular automata, agent based models and data mining. I have successfully completed a number of research projects, to which I bring creativity and a high level of application. I have a strong passion for programming and I am committed to passing on this passion, together with my knowledge.

#### EDUCATION

### University of Cardiff, Cardiff, UK

M.Sc., Computing, Distinction, 2012

• Dissertation Topic: "A naive Bayesian classifier of bacterial Gram stain phenotypes from enzyme functional role"

## University of Sheffield, Sheffield, UK

Ph.D. 2001

• Dissertation Topic: "Individual based models in plant ecology"

https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/195824611/JD-PVR/PVR.html

University of Sussex, Brighton, Sussex UK

M.Sc., Evolutionary and Adaptive Systems (Computing), 1997

Queen Elizabeth College, University of London, London UK

B.Sc., Microbiology

Honours and Awards USA National Research Council Research Associateship Award (2003-2005)

The Cyberlife Scholarship Evolutionary and Adaptive Systems MSc at the School of Cognitive Science, University of Sussex (1996)

British Council travel award AgResearch Palmerston North, New Zealand (1993)

EMPLOYMENT

## Computation Institute, University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois USA

Sr. Computational Biology Research Assistant

2012 -

Dept Surgery, University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois USA  Post doctoral Researcher	2010 - 2011
Dept Surgery, Northwestern University , Chicago, Illinois USA Post doctoral Researcher	2009 - 2010
<b>Dept Mathematics, QUT</b> , Brisbane, Queensland Australia  Post doctoral Researcher	2007 - 2009
CSIRO , Brisbane, Queensland Australia  Post doctoral Researcher	2005 - 2007
Environmental Protection Agency , Corvallis, Oregon USA $NRC\ Research\ fellow$	2003 - 2005
Momentum Healthcare , Cardiff,UK Senior software engineer	1998 - 2001
MHA Productions , London UK  Multimedia Programmer	1996 - 1998
UCPE, University of Sheffield , Sheffield UK Research Associate	1991 - 1996
UKAEA , Harwell UK Research Associate	1987 - 1991
Dept Microbiology, University of Surrey, Gilford, Surry UK Research Associate	1984 - 1987

### **Publications**

E. M. Williams, T. Powell, M. Eriksen, P. Neill, R. Colasanti, 2013, A pilot study quantifying the shape of tidal breathing waveforms using centroids in health and COPD, Journal of Clinical Monitoring and Computing.

Colasanti RL. 2013 A naive Bayesian classifier of bacterial Gram stain phenotypes from enzyme functional roles, A dissertation submitted in partial fulfilment of the requirements for Cardiff University Master of Science Degree in Computing

Watrud, L.S, King, G., Londo, J.P., Colasanti, R.L., Smith, B.S., Waschmann, R.S., and Henry Lee H.E., 2011. Changes in constructed Brassica communities treated with glyphosate drift Ecological Applications 21:2, 525-538

Colasanti, Ricardo, and Gary An. "The abstracted biological computational unit: Introduction of a recursive descriptor for multiscale computational modeling of biological systems." Journal of Critical Care 24.3 (2009): e35-e36.

Graeme J. Pettet, Colin P. Please, Ricardo L.Colasanti, Rebecca and A. Dawson. 2008 A cellular automata simulation of calcium driven tissue dierentiation in human skin equivalent models Automata-2008. Theory and Applications of Cellular Automata. Luniver Press.

Van Klinken, R. D., R. Colasanti, and Y. M. Buckleyzr. "seed predation?." In Proceedings of the Twelfth International Symposium on Biological Control of Weeds, p. 52. CABI, 2008.

Colasanti, Ric, Rieks D. van Klinken, Shaun Coutts, and Yvonne Buckley. "The dynamics of invasion as a function of landscape connectivity." In Proceedings of the 16th Australian Weeds Conference, Cairns Convention Centre, North Queensland, Australia, 18-22 May, 2008., pp. 130-132. Queensland Weed Society, 2008.

Colasanti RL, Hunt R, Watrud L. 2007 A simple cellular automaton model for high-level vegetation dynamics Ecological modelling 203, 363-374.

Hunt R, Colasanti RL 2007 Self-assembling Plants and Integration across Ecological Scales. Annals of Botany 99: 10231034.

Wimpenny J, Colasanti RL 2005 A simple cellular automaton model for coaggregation. Biofilms, 1: 369-375

Colasanti RL, Morris MJ, Madgwick RG, Sutton L and Williams M. 2004 Analysis of tidal breathing profiles in cystic fibrosis and COPD. Chest;125:901-8.

Colasanti RL, Hunt R. and Askew A.P. 2001 A self-assembling model of resource dynamics and

plant growth incorporating plant functional types. Functional Ecology 15: 676-687.

Wimpenny JWT, Colasanti R 1997 A more unifying hypothesis for biofilm structures - a reply FEMS microbiology ecology, 1997, Vol.24, No.2, pp.185-186

Wimpenny JWT, Colasanti RL. 1997 A unifying hypothesis for the structure of microbial biofilms based on cellular automaton models FEMS microbiology ecology, 1997, Vol.22, No.1, pp.1-16

Colasanti RL, Hunt R. 1997. Real Botany with Artificial Plants: A Dynamic, Self-Assembling, Plant Model for Individuals and Populations. In: Husbands P, Harvey D, eds. Fourth European Conference on Artificial Life. MIT Press.

Colasanti RL, Hunt R. 1997. Resource dynamics and plant growth: a self-assembling model for individuals, populations and communities. Functional Ecology 11:133-145.

Hodgson JG, Montserrat G, Alberto F, Garcia-Ruiz JM, Guerrero J, Colasanti RL. 1994. A comparison of the functional characteristics of plants from sedimenting and eroded areas with particular reference to the gypsum hills of the Ebro Depression. In: Arniez J,Garcia-Ruiz JM, Gomez V, eds. Geomorfologia en Espana. Sociedad Espanola de Geomorfologa, Lograono, 239-251.

Hodgson JG, Colasanti R, Phillipson P, Leach S, Montgomery S, Hunt R. 1994. A simple method for monitoring grassland vegetation. In: Haggar RJ, Peel S, eds. Grassland Management and Nature Conservation. Reading: BGS Occasional Symposium No 28: 286-288.

Hodgson JG, Colasanti RL, Alberto F, Montserrat G, Romo A. 1993. Plant strategies and other functional attributes of vegetation from the arid lands: Monegros. Zaragoza: Instituto Pirenaico de Ecologa.

Colasanti RL. Grime JP. 1993. Resource dynamics and vegetation processes: A deterministic model using two dimensional cellular automata. Functional Ecology 7: 169-177. Colasanti RL. 1992. Cellular automata models of microbial colonies. Binary 24: 19-22.

Colasanti RL. 1992. Discussions of the possible use of neural network algorithms in ecological modelling. Binary 3: 13-15.

Colasanti RL, Rosever A, Coutts D, Pugh SYR. 1991. The Microbiology program for UK Nirex. Experientia 47: 560-572.

Colasanti RL. 1988. Modular simulation of a microbial ecosystem with Turbo PROLOG. Binary 13: 24-27.

### PATENTS

Patent Application, Serial No. 09/656,372 (Sept 6, 2000), USA - Method and system for interpreting and validating experimental data with automated reasoning. Case number 00.693. Inventors: Ricardo L Colasanti, Mark A D Collins, John R Shaw

Patent Application, Serial No. 09/655,677 (Sept 6, 2000), USA - Method and system for obtaining knowledge based recommendations. Case number 00.692. Inventors: Mark A D Collins, John R Shaw, Ricardo L Colasanti

Patent Application, Serial No. 09/656,400 (Sept 6, 2000), USA - Method and system for creating and using knowledge patterns. Case number 00694. Inventors: Mark A D Collins, Ricardo L Colasanti

## Computer Skills Current frequent use:

- Languages: Java, Perl, Python, Javascript (libraries Angular JS, Boostrap, JQuery, Node JS).
- Data mining libraries: WEKA, Mahout (Apachie).

### Previous frequent use:

- Statistical/Mathamatical Packages: R, Jump, Octave(Matlab).
- $\bullet$  Languages: C,C++, C # , Fortran,Prolog,Visual Basic

Operating Systems: Unix/Linux, OSX, Windows.